<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file is part of the book    							-->
<!--                                               				-->
<!--   Inquiries into Probability and Statistics - Math S–304	-->
<!--                                                			-->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2016  Thomas W. Judson      					-->

<chapter xml:id="prob-random-var" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Probability Distributions and Random Variables</title>



    <section>
        <title>Random Variables</title>

        <p>A <term>random variable</term> is a function that assigns a number to each point in a sample space.  For example, suppose that we flip two coins.  Our sample space is <m>S = \{ HH, HT, TH , TT \}</m>.  We can let <m>X</m> be the number of heads for each point in the sample space.  Thus, our random variable is defined in the Table<nbsp /><xref ref="table-prob-random-var-1" />.  Random variables are usually denotes by capital lettters such as <m>X</m> or <m>Y</m>.</p>

        <table xml:id="table-prob-random-var-1">
           <tabular halign="center" top="medium">
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell>Sample Point</cell><cell>HH</cell><cell>HT</cell><cell>TH</cell><cell>TT</cell>
                </row>
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell><m>X</m></cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell>
                </row>
           </tabular>
            <caption>Random variable for the number of heads</caption>
        </table>

        <p>Of course, we might define a different random variable on <m>S</m>.  Suppose that you pay <dollar />2 to play a game of chance.  You win <dollar />4 if two coins are tossed and both come up heads; otherwise, you lose your initial investment. Our random variable is now defined in the Table<nbsp /><xref ref="table-prob-random-var-2" />.</p>

        <table xml:id="table-prob-random-var-2">
           <tabular halign="center" top="medium">
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell>Sample Point</cell><cell>HH</cell><cell>HT</cell><cell>TH</cell><cell>TT</cell>
                </row>
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell><m>X</m></cell><cell>4</cell><cell><m>-2</m></cell><cell><m>-2</m></cell><cell><m>-2</m></cell>
                </row>
           </tabular>
            <caption>Random variable for the number of heads</caption>
        </table>

        <p>The question now arises whether or not you should play this game.  In other words, if you play the game over and over again, do you expect to win or lose money.  We define the <term>expected value</term> of a random variable <m>X</m> to be
            <me>E(X) = x_1 P(X = x_1) + x_2 P(X = x_2) + \cdots + x_n P(X = x_n),</me>
        where <m>S = \{x_1, x_2, \ldots, x_n \}</m>.  In our game of chance, our expected value is
            <md>
                <mrow>E(X) \amp = x_1 P(X = HH) + x_2 P(X = HT) + x_3 P(X = TH) + x_4 P(X = TT)</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp = 4 \cdot \frac{1}{4} - 2 \cdot \frac{3}{4} = -\frac{1}{2}.</mrow>
            </md>
        Should your agree to play this game?  Probably not<mdash />If you play this game many times, you will lose an average of <dollar />0.50 each time you play.</p>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>What should you pay to play this game if the game is fair?  That is, what should you pay so that the expected value is zero?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>


        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>The expected value of a random variable has many real world applications.  For example, suppose that you want to insure the bicycles of college students against theft.  After careful research, you decide that there are basically four types of theft<mdash />cheap bicycles that are locked outside, cheap bicycles that kept inside, expensive bicycles that are kept locked outside, and expensive bicycles that are kept inside.  Cheap bicycles can be insured for <dollar />200 per semester and expensive bicycles can be insured for <dollar />1000.  After much research, you decide that the probability that a bicycle kept inside is stolen is 0.01.  The probability that a bicycle that is kept outside will be stolen is 0.2 if it is an inexpensive bicycle but 0.5 if it is expensive.  What is your expected payout over the course of a semester?  What should you charge if you want to make a profit of <dollar />50 per policy?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Probability Distributions</title>

 
    </section>

</chapter>