<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file is part of the book    							-->
<!--                                               				-->
<!--   Inquiries into Probability and Statistics - Math S–304	-->
<!--                                                			-->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2016  Thomas W. Judson      					-->

<chapter xml:id="prob-combinatorics" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

	<title>Combinatorics and Counting Problems</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>If we pose the question, <q>How may ways can we flip three coins?</q> we can simply list all of the possibilities by exhaustion.  In fact, there are eight:
        	<me>\{ HHH, HHT, HTH, THH, HTT, THT, TTH, TTT \}.</me>
        However, the problem is far more difficult if we ask how many ways are there to flip 1000 coins.  In fact, there are <m>2^{1000}</m> ways. Since <m>2^{1000}</m> is a 302 digit number, it really isn't feasible to list all of the possibilities.  We need to be a lot more clever.  In order to compute probabilities of equally likely events in a sample space, we need to learn how to count things.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="section-prob-combinatorics-counting">
        <title>Counting Problems</title>

        <p>This is a section.</p>

        <principle number="no">
			<title>The Fundamental Principle of Counting</title>
			<statement>
				<p>If an event <m>A</m> can occur in <m>m</m> ways and an even <m>B</m> can occur in <m>n</m> ways, then the event <m>A</m> followed by the event <m>B</m> can occur in <m>mn</m> ways.</p>
			</statement>
		</principle>		

    </section>

    <section xml:id="section-prob-combinatorics-comb">
        <title>Combinatorics</title>

        <p>An order or arrangement of people or objects is called a <term>permutation</term>.</p>

        <example>
        	<p>Suppose that we with to elect two officers, a president and a vice-president, from 10 members of a club.  The club members will first elect a president from the 10 club members and will then choose a vice-president from the remaining 9 members. Using the Fundamental Principle of Counting, there are <m>10 \cdot 9 = 90</m> ways to elect a president followed by electing a vice-president.</p>
        </example>

        <p>If <m>n</m> objects are chose <m>r</m> at a time, the number of possible permutations (ordered arrangements) is 
        <me>{}_n P_r = n(n-1)(n-2) \cdot \cdots \cdot (n - r + 1).</me></p>


        <p>The <term>factorial</term> of a positive integer <m>n</m> is defined to be
    		<me>n! = n(n-1)(n-2) \cdot \cdots \cdot 3 \cdot 2 \cdot 1.</me>
    	We define <m>0! = 1</m>.</p>

    	<p>A <term>combination</term> is an arrnagement of people or objects where order is not important.</p>

    	<p>If <m>n</m> objects are chose <m>r</m> at a time, the number of possible combinations (order does not matter) is 
        <me>{}_n C_r = \frac{{}_n P_r }{r!} = \frac{n!}{r!(n-r)!}.</me></p>

        <example>
        	<p>Suppose that we with to elect a committee of 3 people, from 10 members of a club.  If we were electing officers, then the number of possible ways to select three officers is
        		<me>{}_{10} P_3 = 10 \cdot 9 \cdot 8.</me>
        	We could chose a committee of 3 people and then select the officers from the committee.  If we proceed in this manner, then we know that there are exactly <m>3! = 3 \cdot 2 \cdot 1</m> ways of selecting 3 officers from a committee of 3.  Therefore,
        		<me>{}_{10} P_3 = 3! {}_{10} C_3.</me></p>
        </example>

    </section>

    <exercises>
		<title>Exercises</title>

		<exercise number="1">
			<statement>
				<p>Four couples are sitting together in a movie theater.  How may ways can the 8 people be seated without a couple being broken up?</p>
			</statement>
			<hint>
				<p>Try answering the following questions.
					<ol>

						<li><p>How may choices are there for the aisle seat?</p></li>

						<li><p>Once the aisle seat is filled, how many choices are there for the seat next to it?</p></li>

					</ol></p>
			</hint>
			<solution>
				<p>This is the solution.</p>
			</solution>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>

</chapter>