<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file is part of the book    							-->
<!--                                               				-->
<!--   Inquiries into Probability and Statistics - Math S–304	-->
<!--                                                			-->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2016  Thomas W. Judson      					-->

<chapter xml:id="prob-random-var" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Probability Distributions and Random Variables</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>The learning objectives for this chapter are:
            <ul>

                <li>To understand and be able to use random variables.</li>

                <li>To understand and be able to use probability distributions.</li>

                <li>To understand and be able to use normal distributions and standard normal distributions.</li>

                <li>To understand and be able to apply the 68<ndash />95<ndash />99.7 rule.</li>


            </ul></p>
    </introduction>



    <section>
        <title>Random Variables</title>

        <p>A <term>random variable</term> is a function that assigns a number to each point in a sample space.  For example, suppose that we flip two coins.  Our sample space is <m>S = \{ HH, HT, TH , TT \}</m>.  We can let <m>X</m> be the number of heads for each point in the sample space.  Thus, our random variable is defined in the Table<nbsp /><xref ref="table-prob-random-var-1" />.  Random variables are usually denotes by capital lettters such as <m>X</m> or <m>Y</m>.</p>

        <table xml:id="table-prob-random-var-1">
           <tabular halign="center" top="medium">
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell>Sample Point</cell><cell>HH</cell><cell>HT</cell><cell>TH</cell><cell>TT</cell>
                </row>
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell><m>X</m></cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell>
                </row>
           </tabular>
            <caption>Random variable for the number of heads</caption>
        </table>

        <p>Of course, we might define a different random variable on <m>S</m>.  Suppose that you pay <dollar />2 to play a game of chance.  You win <dollar />4 if two coins are tossed and both come up heads; otherwise, you lose your initial investment. Our random variable is now defined in the Table<nbsp /><xref ref="table-prob-random-var-2" />.</p>

        <table xml:id="table-prob-random-var-2">
           <tabular halign="center" top="medium">
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell>Sample Point</cell><cell>HH</cell><cell>HT</cell><cell>TH</cell><cell>TT</cell>
                </row>
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell><m>X</m></cell><cell>4</cell><cell><m>-2</m></cell><cell><m>-2</m></cell><cell><m>-2</m></cell>
                </row>
           </tabular>
            <caption>Random variable for the number of heads</caption>
        </table>

        <p>The question now arises whether or not you should play this game.  In other words, if you play the game over and over again, do you expect to win or lose money.  We define the <term>expected value</term> of a random variable <m>X</m> to be
            <me>E(X) = x_1 P(X = x_1) + x_2 P(X = x_2) + \cdots + x_n P(X = x_n),</me>
        where <m>S = \{x_1, x_2, \ldots, x_n \}</m>.  In our game of chance, our expected value is
            <md>
                <mrow>E(X) \amp = x_1 P(X = HH) + x_2 P(X = HT) + x_3 P(X = TH) + x_4 P(X = TT)</mrow>
                <mrow>\amp = 4 \cdot \frac{1}{4} - 2 \cdot \frac{3}{4} = -\frac{1}{2}.</mrow>
            </md>
        Should your agree to play this game?  Probably not<mdash />If you play this game many times, you will lose an average of <dollar />0.50 each time you play.</p>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>What should you pay to play this game if the game is fair?  That is, what should you pay so that the expected value is zero?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <example>
            <p>Suppose that <m>X</m> denotes the number obtained in a roll of a fair die, then the expected value of <m>X</m> is 3.5. Of course, <m>X</m> will never be be 3.5, but if we roll a die 10,000 and record the value of each roll, then we can expect the average of all of these rolls to be somewhere near 3.5.</p>
        </example>

        <example>
            <p>Suppose the premium of a home insurance policy is <dollar />300 and in case of a fire the insurance company will pay out <dollar />200,000. If <m>X</m> denotes the profit (or loss) of such a policy, then <m>X</m> is a random variable. The expected value of <m>X</m> depends on the probability of a fire <m>p</m>. If, for example, <m>p = 0.0002</m>, then <m>X = 300</m> with probability <m>1- p = 0.9998</m> when there is no fire,  and <m>X = -200,000 + 300 = -199,700</m> with probability <m>p = 0.0002</m> when there is a fire. Consequently, the expected value of <m>X</m> is 
                <me>E(X) = 300 \cdot 0.9998 + (-199700) \cdot 0.0002 = 260.</me> 
            This means if the insurance company issues 10000 such policies, it can expect to profit <dollar />2,600,000.</p>
        </example>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Suppose that you want to insure the bicycles of college students against theft.  After careful research, you decide that there are basically four types of theft<mdash />cheap bicycles that are locked outside, cheap bicycles that kept inside, expensive bicycles that are kept locked outside, and expensive bicycles that are kept inside.  Cheap bicycles can be insured for <dollar />200 per semester and expensive bicycles can be insured for <dollar />1000.  After much research, you decide that the probability that a bicycle kept inside is stolen is 0.001.  The probability that a bicycle that is kept outside will be stolen is 0.2 if it is an inexpensive bicycle but 0.5 if it is expensive.  What is your expected payout over the course of a semester?  What should you charge if you want to make a profit of <dollar />30 per policy?  Should you offer two different types of policies<mdash />one for bicycles stored outside and one for bicycles stored inside?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Probability Distributions</title>

        <p>The probability distribution of a random variable <m>X</m> tells us how to assign probabilities to a random variable.  More specifically, for a random variable <m>X</m> on a sample space <m>S = \{x_1, x_2, \ldots, x_n\}</m>, a <term>probability distribution</term> is a function
            <me>f(x_i) = P(X = x_i)</me>
        such that 
            <ol>
                <li><m>f(x_i) \geq 0</m></li>

                <li><m>\displaystyle\sum_{i = 1}^n f(x_1) = 1</m></li>

            </ol>
        </p>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Suppose that we flip four coins and let <m>X</m> be the number of heads.  What is the probability distribution of <m>X</m>?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>We also have the notion of a continuous random variable, or a random variable that can take on an infinite number of values.  For example, suppose that <m>S</m> is all of the numbers between zero and one.  We define a random variable <m>X</m> on <m>S</m> just to be the value of the number in the interval <m>0 \leq x \leq 1</m>.
                    <ol>
                        <li>What is <m>P(X \leq 0.5)</m>?</li>

                        <li>What is <m>P(0.4 \leq X \leq 0.5)</m>?</li>

                        <li>What is <m>P(0.49 \leq X \leq 0.5)</m>?</li>

                        <li>What is <m>P(0.499 \leq X \leq 0.5)</m>?</li>

                        <li>What is <m>P(0.4999 \leq X \leq 0.5)</m>?</li>

                        <li>What is <m>P(X = 0.5)</m>?</li>

                    </ol>
                </p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <p>For the definition of a continuous random variable, we replace the axiom
            <me>\sum_{i = 1}^n f(x_1) = 1</me>
        with a calculus integral
            <me>\int_{-\infty}^\infty f(x) \, dx = 1.</me>
        For those who have studied calculus, you will begin to see how everything works.  If you haven't studied calculus, you will not need it for this course.  However, this course may provide some motivation to study the subject.</p>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Normal Distributions</title>

        <p>Continuous probability distributions are important, since we can use them to model many real world situations.  For example, a very important class of continuous probability distribution is the <term>normal distribution</term>.  The normal distribution has probability function
            <men xml:id="equation-prob-random-var-normal">f(x) = \frac{1}{\sigma \sqrt{2 \pi}} e^{-(x - \mu)^2/2 \sigma^2},</men>
        and its graph is a symmetric, bell-shaped curve (Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-prob-random-var-normal" />).  The parameter <m>\mu</m> is called the <term>mean</term> of the distribution and tells us where the curve is centered.  The parameter <m>\sigma</m> is the <term>standard deviation</term> of the distribution and tells us how spread out the curve is.  Changing <m>\mu</m> just moves the curve back and forth along the horizontal axis without changing the shape of the curve.  Remember that the area between the curve and the horizontal axis will always be 1 no matter how we change <m>\mu</m> or <m>\sigma</m>.  The parameter <m>\sigma</m> must be a positive number.  Small values of <m>\sigma</m> will give us a comapct curve with a high peak.  Larger values will result in a curve that is more spread out. The good news is that we do not have to remember the complicated function <xref ref="equation-prob-random-var-normal" /> for our course.</p>

        <figure xml:id="figure-prob-random-var-normal">
            <caption>Normal distributions</caption>
            <image width="250" source="images/normal-dist.png" />
        </figure>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Find examples of populations that are approximately normally distributed.  Find some examples of populations that are not normally distributed.</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <paragraphs>
            <title>The 68<ndash />95<ndash />99.7 Rule</title>

          <p>All normal distributions satisfy the following rule.  For a normal distribution with mean <m>\mu</m> and standard deviation <m>\sigma</m>:
                <ul>

                    <li>68<percent /> of the observations fall within <m>\sigma</m> of the mean <m>\mu</m>.</li>

                    <li>95<percent /> of the observations fall within <m>2\sigma</m> of the mean <m>\mu</m>.</li>

                    <li>99.7<percent /> of the observations fall within <m>3\sigma</m> of the mean <m>\mu</m>.</li>

                </ul></p>
        </paragraphs>

        <example>
            <p>The distribution of heights of American women between the ages of 18 and 24 is approximately normal with mean <m>\mu = 64.5</m> inches and standard deviation <m>\sigma = 2.5</m> inches. The 68<ndash />95<ndash />99.7 rule tells us that 68<percent /> of American women between the ages of 18 and 24 will be between 62 inches tall and 67 inches tall.</p>
        </example>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p><ol>

                    <li>What percentage of women are taller than 67 inches?</li>

                    <li>What percentage of women are shorter than 62 inches?</li>

                    <li>What percentage of women are between 59.5 and 69.5 inches tall?</li>

                    <li>What percentage of women are taller than 72 inches?</li>

                </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>The lengths of human pregnancies are approximately normally distributed with a mean of 266 days and a standard deviation of 16 days.
                    <ol>

                        <li>What percent of pregnancies last at most 240 days?</li>

                        <li>What percent of pregnancies last from 240 to 280 days?</li>

                        <li>What percentage of pregnancies last longer than 298 days></li>

                        <li>Why do we use the phrase <q><em>approximately</em> normally distributed?</q></li>

                    </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>A tire company tests a particular tire and finds the tires to be normally distributed with respect to wear.  The mean is 28,000 miles and the standard deviation is 2500 miles.  If 2000 tires are tested, use 68<ndash />95<ndash />99.7 rule to determine how many tires will wear out before 23,000 miles.</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>The New York Knights baseball team finds that the attendance at its home games at Ebbets Field is normally distributed, with a mean of 10,000 and a standard deviation of 3000.  Use the 68<ndash />95<ndash />99.7 rule to answer the following questions.
                    <ol>

                        <li>What percent of home games have an attendance between 4,000 and 16,000 people?</li>

                        <li>What percent of home games have an attendance of more than 13,000 people?</li>

                        <li>Who are the New York Knights?</li>

                </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <p>Suppose that <m>x</m> is an observed value from a normal distribution with mean <m>\mu</m> and standard deviation <m>\sigma</m>.  The <term>standardized value</term> of <m>x</m> is
            <me>z = \frac{x - \mu}{\sigma}.</me>
        The standardized value is sometimes called the <term><m>z</m>-score</term>.  A <m>z</m>-score tells us how many standard deviations the observation <m>x</m> is away from the mean.  Positive <m>z</m>-scores are larger than the mean and negative <m>z</m>-score are smaller than the mean.</p>

        <example>
            <p>For the lengths of human pregnancies, <m>\mu = 266</m> days and <m>\sigma = 16</m> days. Thus, the <m>z</m>-score is given by 
                <me>z = \frac{\text{length of pregnancy} - \mu}{\sigma} = \frac{\text{length of pregnancy} - 266}{16}.</me>
            Suppose that the length of a pregnancy is 280 days.  Then the <m>z</m>-score for this pregnancy is
                <me>z = \frac{280 - 266}{16} = 0.875</me>
            or 0.875 standard deviations above the mean.  Similarly, a pregnancy of 230 days has a <m>z</m>-score
                <me>z = \frac{230 - 266}{16} = -2.25</me>
            or 2.25 standard deviations below the mean.</p>
        </example>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>The weights of newborn babies are normally distributed with a mean of approximately 105 oz and a standard deviation of 20 oz.
                    <ol>

                        <li>What is the probability that a newborn baby selected at random weighs less than 125 oz?</li>

                        <li>What is the probability that a newborn baby selected at random weighs more than 125 oz?</li>

                        <li>What is the probability that a newborn baby selected at random weighs between 85 oz and 145 oz?</li>

                    </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <p>Of particular importance is the <term>standard normal distribution</term>.  This is the normal distribution where <m>\mu = 0</m> and <m>\sigma = 1</m>. Standardizing a variable of any normal distribution produces a new variable with a standard normal distribution.  In other words, if a variable <m>x</m> has a normal distribution with mean <m>\mu</m> and standard deviation <m>\sigma</m>, then
            <me>z = \frac{x - \mu}{\sigma}</me>
        has the standard normal distribution.  Tables (see Figure<nbsp /><xref ref="figure-prob-random-var-z-table" />), calculators, or software will give the area under the standard normal curve for a particular value of <m>z</m>.</p>

        <figure xml:id="figure-prob-random-var-z-table">
            <caption>Standard normal distribution</caption>
            <image width="350" source="images/z-table.jpg" />
        </figure>

        <example xml:id="example-prob-random-var-z-table">
            <p>A pregnancy of 280 days has a <m>z</m>-score of 0.875.  Looking at the standard normal table, we can determine that approximately 81<percent /> of all pregnancies last 280 days or less.  Similarly, a pregnancy of 230 days has a <m>z</m>-score of  <m>-2.25</m>.  Consulting our table, we see that only 1.2<percent /> of all pregnancies last 230 days or less.</p>
        </example>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Use the standard normal distribution table to find each of the following.
                    <ol>
                        <li><m>z \leq 1.25</m></li>

                        <li><m>z \leq -1.25</m></li>

                        <li><m>-1.25 \leq z \leq 1.25</m></li>

                        <li><m>z \gt 1.25</m></li>

                        <li><m>-1.34 \leq z \leq 1.75</m></li>

                        <li><m>-1.34 \lt z \lt 1.75</m></li>

                        <li><m>z = 1.25</m></li>


                    </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Explain how the <m>z</m>-scores in Example<nbsp /><xref ref="example-prob-random-var-z-table" /> are obtained from the standard normal distribution table.</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Ty Cobb's batting average was .420 in 1911, Ted Williams batted .406 in 1941, and George Brett batted .390 in 1980.  If we ask how this baseball players compared to their peers, the story is a bit more complicated than just comparing their batting averages directly.  If we look at batting averages for all players for each of these years, the distribution is approximately normal; however, the means and standard deviations vary.  See Table<nbsp /><xref ref="table-prob-random-batting-averages" />.  Which of the three players was better than his peers?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <table xml:id="table-prob-random-batting-averages">
           <tabular halign="center" top="medium">
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell>Decade</cell><cell>Mean (<m>\mu</m>)</cell><cell>Standard Deviation (<m>\sigma</m>)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1910s</cell><cell>.266</cell><cell>0.0371</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1940s</cell><cell>.267</cell><cell>0.0326</cell>
                </row>
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell>1970s</cell><cell>.261</cell><cell>0.0317</cell>
                </row>
           </tabular>
            <caption>Distribution of batting averages</caption>
        </table>

 
    </section>

</chapter>