<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file is part of the book    							-->
<!--                                               				-->
<!--   Inquiries into Probability and Statistics - Math S–304	-->
<!--                                                			-->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2016  Thomas W. Judson      					-->

<chapter xml:id="prob-combinatorics" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

	<title>Combinatorics and Counting Problems</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>If we pose the question, <q>How may ways can we flip three coins?</q> we can simply list all of the possibilities by exhaustion.  In fact, there are eight:
        	<me>\{ HHH, HHT, HTH, THH, HTT, THT, TTH, TTT \}.</me>
        However, the problem is far more difficult if we ask how many ways are there to flip 1000 coins.  In fact, there are <m>2^{1000}</m> ways. Since <m>2^{1000}</m> is a 302 digit number, it really isn't feasible to list all of the possibilities.  We need to be a lot more clever.  In order to compute probabilities of equally likely events in a sample space, we need to learn how to count things.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="section-prob-combinatorics-counting">
        <title>Counting Problems</title>

         <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Samantha is packing for a week long trip to Paris, and deciding if she has enough different outfits to wear while touring the City of Light.  If she packs three different skirts and four different blouses, how many different skirt-blouse combinations can she make?  Draw a tree diagram to illustrate your conclusion.</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <principle number="no">
			<title>The Fundamental Principle of Counting</title>
			<statement>
				<p>If an event <m>A</m> can occur in <m>m</m> ways and an even <m>B</m> can occur in <m>n</m> ways, then the event <m>A</m> followed by the event <m>B</m> can occur in <m>mn</m> ways.</p>
			</statement>
		</principle>

         <exercise>
          	<statement>
                <p>A committee of three people is to be formed consisting of one representative from management, one representative from labor, and one representative from the general public.  If there are 4 possible representatives from labor, 2 from management, and 5 from the public, how many different ways can the committee be formed?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="section-prob-combinatorics-permute">
        <title>Permutations</title>

        <p>An order or arrangement of people or objects is called a <term>permutation</term>.</p>

        <example>
        	<p>Suppose that we with to elect two officers, a president and a vice-president, from 10 members of a club.  The club members will first elect a president from the 10 club members and will then choose a vice-president from the remaining 9 members. Using the Fundamental Principle of Counting, there are <m>10 \cdot 9 = 90</m> ways to elect a president followed by electing a vice-president.</p>
        </example>

        <p>If <m>n</m> objects are chose <m>r</m> at a time, the number of possible permutations (ordered arrangements) is 
        <me>{}_n P_r = n(n-1)(n-2) \cdot \cdots \cdot (n - r + 1).</me></p>


        <p>The <term>factorial</term> of a positive integer <m>n</m> is defined to be
    		<me>n! = n(n-1)(n-2) \cdot \cdots \cdot 3 \cdot 2 \cdot 1.</me>
    	We define <m>0! = 1</m>.</p>


    </section>

    <section xml:id="section-prob-combinatorics-combinations">
        <title>Combinations</title>


    	<p>A <term>combination</term> is an arrangement of people or objects where order is not important.  For example, suppose that we have a club consisting of three people: Alice, Bob, and Carol.  Electing Alice, Bob, and Carol to a committee, is quite different than choosing a president, vice-president, and secretary from these three people.  There are six ways that we can elect officers but only one way that we can elect a committee of three.</p>

    	<example>
        	<p>Suppose that we with to elect a committee of 3 people, from 10 members of a club.  If we were electing officers, then the number of possible ways to select three officers is
        		<me>{}_{10} P_3 = 10 \cdot 9 \cdot 8.</me>
        	We could chose a committee of 3 people and then select the officers from the committee.  If we proceed in this manner, then we know that there are exactly <m>3! = 3 \cdot 2 \cdot 1</m> ways of selecting 3 officers from a committee of 3.  Therefore,
        		<me>{}_{10} P_3 = 3! {}_{10} C_3.</me></p>
        </example>

    	<p>If <m>n</m> objects are chose <m>r</m> at a time, the number of possible combinations (order does not matter) is 
        	<me>{}_n C_r = \frac{{}_n P_r }{r!} = \frac{n!}{r!(n-r)!}.</me>
        We sometimes write
        	<me>\binom{n}{r} = {}_n C_r = \frac{n!}{r!(n-r)!}.</me></p>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Make an argument that 
                	<me>{}_n C_r = \frac{{}_n P_r }{r!} = \frac{n!}{r!(n-r)!}</me>
               	correctly describes the number of possible combinations of <m>r</m> objects chosen from a total number of <m>n</m> objects.</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

    </section>

    <section>
    	<title>Putting Everything Together</title>

    	<exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>If a coin is tossed 5 times, how many different ways can the sequence of heads and tails appear?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Four couples are sitting together in a movie theater.
                    <ol>

                        <li><p>How may choices are there for the aisle seat?</p></li>

                        <li><p>Once the aisle seat is filled, how many choices are there for the seat next to it?</p></li>

                        <li><p>How may ways can the 8 people be seated without a couple being broken up?</p></li>

                    </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>



        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>The eight-grade class at a middle school has 16 girls and 14 boys.  How many different boy-girl dates can be arranged?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Three Aces Pizza offers 3 kinds of salads, 15 kinds of pizza, and 4 kinds of dessert.  How many different three-course meals can be ordered?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>How many ways can the letters in the word <em>SCRAMBLE</em> be arranged?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>How many <em>different</em> ways can the letters in the word <em>MISSISSIPPI</em> be arranged?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Assume that a class has 30 members.
                    <ol>

                        <li><p>How many ways can a president, a vice president, and a secretary be elected?</p></li>

                        <li><p>How many committees of 3 people can be chosen?</p></li>

                    </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>In a certain lottery game, 54 numbers are randomly mixed and 6 are selected.  A person must pick all 6 numbers to win.
                    <ol>

                        <li><p>What is the probability of winning if order is not important?</p></li>

                        <li><p>What is the probability of winning if order is important?</p></li>

                    </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>A true/false quiz has five questions.  What is the probability of getting at least four correct answers by guessing.</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>A quiz has four multiple-choice questions.  Each question has five choices and only one choice is the correct answer.  Suppose that you guess on all four questions.
                    <ol>

                        <li><p>If you got at least three correct answers, how many questions could you have gotten right?</p></li>

                        <li><p>What is the probability that you answered at least three questions correctly?</p></li>

                    </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Four different mathematics books, six different physics books, and two different chemistry books are to be arranged on a shelf.
                    <ol>

                        <li><p>How many different arrangements are possible if the books in each particular subject must all stand together?</p></li>

                        <li><p>How many different arrangements are possible if only the mathematics books must stand together?</p></li>

                    </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>You are playing poker and you have been dealt a hand of 5 cards from a well shuffled deck.  What is the probability of drawing four aces?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Exactly 20 horse will be entered into the 2015 Kentucky Derby.
                    <ol>

                        <li>How may ways can the first, second, and third-place horse be determined?</li>

                        <li>What is the <em>probability</em> that the top three horses will be <em>Carpe Diem</em>, <em>Upstart</em>, and <em>Daredevil</em>?<fn>Assume that you don't know the results of the 2015 Kentucky Derby.</fn></li>
                </ol></p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>






    </section>







</chapter>