<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file is part of the book    							-->
<!--                                               				-->
<!--   Inquiries into Probability and Statistics - Math S–304	-->
<!--                                                			-->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2016  Thomas W. Judson      					-->

<chapter xml:id="stat-descript" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Introduction to Statistics and Descriptive Statistics</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>The learning objectives for this chapter are:
        	<ul>
        		<li>To understand how data collection methods differ and how they affect the nature of the data set.</li>

        		<li>To understand and be able to evaluate different design studies.</li>
        	</ul></p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="section-stat-populations">
        <title>Populations and Samples</title>

        <exercise>
        	<statement>
        		<p>Lily Robinson is running for the U.S. Senate in Utah.  In a poll of 1,400 voters, 428 voters support her.
        			<ol>
        				<li>What is the population for this poll?</li>

        				<li>If <m>P</m> people vote in the election, what is a good prediction of the number that will vote for Ms.Robinson?</li>
        			</ol></p>
    		</statement>
    	</exercise>

    	<exercise>
        	<statement>
        		<p>A survey of shoppers shows that 20 prefer whole milk, 42 prefer low-fat milk, 28 prefer skim milk, and 10 prefer soy milk.
        			<ol>
        				<li>If 600 shoppers come to the store tomorrow, predict how many will buy each kind of milk.</li>

        				<li>Explain how you made your prediction.</li>
        			</ol></p>
    		</statement>
    	</exercise>

    	<exercise>
        	<statement>
        		<p>Classify each of the following as simple random sampling, stratified sampling, or convenience sampling.
        			<ol>
        				<li>A student newspaper selects 10 names at random from the entire student body.</li>

        				<li>A student newspaper interviews proportional numbers of freshmen, sophomores, juniors, and seniors.</li>

        				<li>A researcher interviews all AIDS patients in the hospital closest to the researcher's home.</li>

        			</ol></p>
    		</statement>
    	</exercise>

    	<exercise>
        	<statement>
        		<p>Describe how to take a sample of 30 high school seniors from  300 high school seniors using
        			<ol>
        				<li>a simple random sample.</li>

        				<li>stratified sampling.</li>

        				<li>voluntary response sampling.</li>
        				
        			</ol></p>
    		</statement>
    	</exercise>

    	<exercise>
        	<statement>
        		<p>A sample of 50 people is obtained to rate <em>Frosted-Chocolate Sugar Bombs</em>, a breakfast cereal.  Tell whether each of the following is an example of undercoverage, nonresponse, or response bias.
        			<ol>
        				<li>An interviewer visits a randomly selected set of homes and asks the first 50 people who answer the door whether they eat <em>Frosted-Chocolate Sugar Bombs</em> for breakfast.</li>

        				<li>An interviewer goes to the local Partial Foods Market and observes what breakfast foods 50 shoppers select.</li>
        				
        			</ol></p>
    		</statement>
    	</exercise>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="section-stat-descript">
        <title>Descriptive Statistics</title>


		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>For each of the following data sets, determine whether the best choice to represent the data graphically is a line graph, a bar graph, or a circle graph (pie chart).
					<ol>

						<li>The average trade-in value of a 2000 Honda Civic for the years 2000<ndash />2014 as a percentage of the original purchase price of the car.</li>

						<li>Car sales by percentage of vehicle type (small, midsize, large, and luxury) in 2011.</li>

						<li>The lengths of selected rivers in the U.S. (Arkansas, Columbia, Mississippi, Missouri, Ohio, and Yukon).</li>

					</ol></p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>



		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>The data below show the number of car thefts in Central City for a period of 20 days.</p>
				
				<p>29 48 49 50 52 53 53 55 56 62 65 66 66 69 72 72 75 78 78 82</p>

				<p><ol>

					<li>Construct a stem-and-leaf plot of the data.</li>

					<li>Are there any outliers?</li>

					<li>What is the five-number summary of the data?</li>

					<li>The five-number summary of data for car thefts in Starling City over the same 20 day period is 
						<me>(\min = 30, Q_1 = 40, \text{median} = 55, Q_3 = 70, \max = 90).</me>
					Compare the number of car thefts in the two cities drawing two box-and-whisker plots.</li>

					<li>How do car thefts compare in the two cities?</li>

				</ol></p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>The final medal standings of the top 20 countries participating in the 2008 Summer Olympics are given below:</p>
				
				<p>110, 100, 72, 47, 46, 41, 40, 31, 28, 27, 25, 24, 19, 18, 18, 16, 15, 14, 13, 11</p>

				<p><ol>

					<li>Find the five-number summary for the 2008 Summer Olympics (min, <m>Q_1</m>, median, <m>Q_3</m>, max).</li>

					<li>Are there any outliers?  If so, what are they?</li>

					<li>The 2012 Summer Olympics has a five-number summary of (12, 17, 24, 40, 104).  Draw side-by-side a box-and-whisker plots for these two data sets.</li>

					<li>How do the 2008 and 2012 Summer Olympics compare?</li>

				</ol></p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>Jill was 80th in a class of 200, whereas Nathan, who is in the same class, has a percentile rank of 80.  Which student has the higher standing in the class?</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>

	</section>

</chapter>