<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2015 Robert A. Beezer

This file is part of MathBook XML.

MathBook XML is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 2 or version 3 of the
License (at your option).

MathBook XML is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file is part of the book    							-->
<!--                                               				-->
<!-- Inquiries into Probability and Statistics - Math S–304		-->
<!--                                                			-->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2016  Thomas W. Judson      					-->

<chapter xml:id="stats-measures" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Measuring Central Tendency and Spread</title>

    <introduction>
        <p>Introduction here.</p>
    </introduction>

    <section xml:id="section-stats-measures-center">
        <title>Measuring the Center</title>

        <p>This is a section.</p>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="section-stats-measures-spread">
        <title>Measuring Spread</title>

        <exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>Jack and Jill are students in two different sections of MTH 128.  Both took exams last week on the data analysis chapter, although the exams were different for the two sections.  In Jack's class, the mean score of all of the exams was 78 with standard deviation 8.  Jill's class did not do quite as well.  The mean score in her class was only 70 with standard deviation 5.  If Jack scored an 90 and Jill scored an 80, who did better on the exam compared to the other students in their respective sections?</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>Matilda intends to go to graduate school and just completed the GRE exam (similar to the SAT exam but for students applying to graduate school).  She scored in the 90th percentile on the GRE exam.  Which of the following is true about Matilda's performance on the GRE?
					<ol>

						<li>Matilda's score is 90<percent /> of the average score.</li>

						<li>Matilda got 90<percent /> of the questions right.</li>

						<li>90<percent /> of test takers scored at or below Matilda's score.</li>

						<li>Matilda scored 90<percent /> better than the average student who took the GRE.</li>

					</ol>
				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>

		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>In the <em>2014 Michelin Guide to Pizza Restaurants in Texas</em>, each restaurant has ten of their best selling pizzas rated on a scale of 0 to 100, with 100 be a perfect score.  The <em>Michelin Guide</em> publishes the mean and standard deviation of top ten pizzas for each restaurant.  For example, <em>Three Aces Pizza</em> has a mean of 70 and a standard deviation of 15.  If your friend asks you for a recommendation, you should select a restaurant with
					<ol>

						<li>a low mean and a low standard deviation.</li>

						<li>a high mean and a low standard deviation.</li>

						<li>a low mean and a high standard deviation.</li>

						<li>a high mean and a high standard deviation.</li>

					</ol></p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>



    </section>

</chapter>